<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brothers gift containing an hundred precepts, instructing all sorts of people to a godly, honest, and morall life.</title>
            <author>Everinden, Humphrey.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114633</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849858</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849858</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 789:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brothers gift containing an hundred precepts, instructing all sorts of people to a godly, honest, and morall life.</title>
                  <author>Everinden, Humphrey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Eld] for Iohn Wright, and are to be sold at his hop at the signe of the Bible without Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle" signed: Humphrey Everinden.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BROTHERS <hi>GJFT: Containing</hi> AN HVNDRED PRECEPTS, Inſtructing all ſorts of people to a godly, honeſt, and morall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Bible without <hi>Newgate.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS LOVING Couſin M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Smith,</hi> all health, grace, and <hi>happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccept good Couſin, a ſmall token of my loue: value not the heart according to the greatnes of the gift; onely taſte and trye, and you ſhall finde it, though ſmall, yet not altogether fruitleſſe, eſpecially if after tryall you truſt and make vſe thereof. Your kinde accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this ſhall be a meanes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb facs="tcp:15030:3"/> a better: So wiſhing Gods grace and bleſſing to you and all your righteous endeuours I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your euer louing Couſin <hi>HVMPHRY EVERINDEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:3"/>
            <head>A BROTHERS <hi>GJFT:</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdge not of Religion by the tongue, but by the life: the heart thou canſt not ſearch, and the life doth more plainly bewray the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of the heart then the tongue: for <hi>it is an eaſy thing and cheap to ſpeake well, but coſtly and laborious to doe well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Neuer call or account a man which is truly and abſolutely couetous, Religious: thou mayeſt as well call an open adulterer or common drunkatd, Religious: for Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes is as contrary to religion as the
<pb facs="tcp:15030:4"/> other, as much hope of the other as of the couetous: and the couetous ſhould as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly be accounted not religious as the other, but that <hi>His filthineſſe is couered with the cloake of thrift, his parſimonie with a pretence of not nouriſhing the poor in idleneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Auoid the company of a couetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as thou wouldeſt the company of a Thiefe, Whoremaſter, or Drunkard: for he is the moſt dangerous thiefe, becauſe by the Lawes vnpuniſhable; he is as ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as the other, becauſe as odious to God, and as ſinfull: <hi>His company is more dangerous then the others, becauſe his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is not accounted ſin, therefore not accounted dangerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Be ſure (frequenting Sermons) to be perfect in the firſt principles of Religion: for <hi>As it is impoſſible for him to reade well that knoweth not his Letters; ſo is it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to reape any full fruit by hearing of Sermons, not well knowing the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:15030:4"/>
               <hi>5</hi> Receiue the Sacrament of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt often: no Spirituall exerciſe is to be vſed ſeldome: <hi>The Word without the Sacraments, is like a Writing of Confirmation without a Seale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> If the Lord haue ſent into thine owne Pariſh a Preacher, on the Sabbath heare him: for if he be bound to feed the flocke of God which dependeth on him, his flocke is bound to receiue their food on him: If thou goe from him, for contempt; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what our Sauiour ſaid of <hi>Iudas</hi> as well as of the other Apoſtles, <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Receiue the Sacrament of the Lords Body and Bloud, alwayes humbly knée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: thinke not that ſo doing thou ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the Bread, for thou maiſt adore the Bread as well ſitting or ſtanding: and if thy heart be frée from ſuperſtition, the thrée geſtures are in themſelues frée, and being in themſelues frée, obey thy Prince in that one of them, that hee commanded for conſcience ſake. <hi>To vrge the ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:15030:5"/> Commandement againſt kneeling at the Sacrament, is vngodly and prophanely to make and account the Sacrament an Idoll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Heare the word of God often: ſay not thou canſt heare enough at one Sermon to practiſe a long time after; for there muſt be line vpon line, precept vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: becauſe all the food thou receiueſt at one meale turneth not into the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy body, thou therefore eateſt againe, and often: So becauſe <hi>All thou heareſt at one Sermon is not remembred, nor at large practiſed of thee, thou alſo muſt heare againe and often.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Deſire in prayer to be frequent in heart, not eloquent in words: the Lord (to whom thou ſpeakeſt) is not like thoſe itching eares which regard to heare no Sermons but ſuch as are polliſhed with eloquence fitted to their humors, pounced with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of learned Arts: but <hi>The ſimplicity of the heart pleaſeth him beſt, and what is to him moſt acceptable, ſhall be with him moſt auailable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb facs="tcp:15030:5"/>
               <hi>10</hi> Be not long in Prayer, but often: long continuance, at one time, dulleth the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (ſuch is our weakneſſe) and the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction dulled the prayer is dead: ſince, then lips labour, and not the heart: yet fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency in Prayer, encreaſeth the feruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the affection, and the feruent cry of the affection pierceth far: ſo that <hi>The fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenter the Spirit, the neerer his groanes aſcend to the eares of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Chuſe ſuch a Trade of life, as wherein with honeſt Art and gaines, thou mayeſt maintaine thine eſtate, not ſuch an one, as wherein without couſoning ſhifts thou canſt not gaine: ſome trades of life now vſed, are in the firſt inſtitution vnlawfull; others in their firſt inſtitution lawfull, yet, as now they are vſed, vnlawfull: a third ſort, by the vngodly, with couſoning ſhifts abuſed, but, <hi>By the honeſt and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with ſincerity lawfully vſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Meaſure out the day into ſet portions, appointing to euery of thy actions, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be performed, his times of the day, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15030:6"/> continuance of time and in euery day, let God haue ſome time ſpared from thy labours: and if extraordinary occaſions with-call thée to interrupt thy appointed order, rather take the time from thy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which in the ſixe dayes is the largeſt, then from the Lords, which is the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> As the Sabbath is wholly to be ſpent in Gods ſeruice, excepting ſome time for thy neceſſary refection, or perhaps recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, or vpon extraordinary occaſion for the preſeruation of the life of Man or Beaſt: So the wéeke dayes are wholly to be ſpent in thy calling (not in Idleneſſe) excepting alſo ſome time for the priuate worſhip of God, or vpon extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, for his publike ſeruice: yet, <hi>Delay not at any time of the day, or in any day of the weeke, in thy labours, going, riding, or ſitting, to lift vp thy heart vnto God, the minde will be alwayes buſied, and better ſuch thoughts then other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> In the Morning, remember thy birth; that as the Sunne riſeth, not to ſtand ſtill, but to goe forward, not to darken, but to
<pb facs="tcp:15030:6"/> enlighten the earth: ſo thou waſt borne, not to continue a childe, but encreaſe in true knowledge of thy Creator, <hi>By the light of a godly conuerſation to glorifie thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> At Noone, remember thy middle age; that as the Sunne when hée is at the higheſt, declineth without ſtaying, ſo thou <hi>In thy greateſt ſtrength ſhall not ſtay, but in a moment decreaſe, and deſcend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Graue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16</hi> At Night, remember thy graue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thy bed is a figure; and thy death, whereof ſléepe is an image: remember that as the Sunne ſetteth, the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ariſe againe, to begin either a faire day or a foule: ſo ſhalt thou ly downe in the duſt, at the Reſurrection, to ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>If thou haue done well, to glorious life and light;</hi> but <hi>If thou haue done euill, to euerlaſting darkeneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17</hi> Make conſcience all the day to follow thy vocation diligently, as in all thy life to embrace Righteouſneſſe ſincerely: for
<pb facs="tcp:15030:7"/> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt giue as certaine account of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, as of thy deedes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18</hi> Be warie and héedfull in thy dealings, not to be couſoned or ouer-reached of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, for this heede is godly and honeſt; yet it will be ſaid, ſimplicitie is a iewell, and Chriſtians muſt bée as little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: truth, <hi>agendo;</hi> not alwaies <hi>patiendo: <hi>In doing; not alwayes in ſuffering:</hi>
               </hi> for he that hath commended the ſimplicitie of the Doue; that is, ſimplicitie without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, hath alſo <hi>Commanded the wiſdome of the Serpent;</hi> that is, <hi>warineſſe without guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19</hi> Before and after meate, giue GOD thanks, partly for Gods ſake, partly for thine owne: for Gods ſake, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him the giuer to his glory for thine owne ſake, <hi>To obtaine his bleſſing to thy comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20</hi> In féeding be ſober: yet pine not the body for want of foode, remembring, that the Golden meane is beſt in all things; and that thou mayeſt offend in either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame,
<pb facs="tcp:15030:7"/> in the exceſſe, and alſo in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: if he be blameable, which hauing this worldly goods, doth not feede and refreſh his poore hungry brother, <hi>Much more is he faulty and cruell, that pineth his owne body for want of foode.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21</hi> Account it as grieuous a ſinne to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thy body with meate, as with drinke: God who hath commanded the ſober vſe of his Creatures, hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſober vſe of the one as well as of the other: and therefore the exceſſe in the one, is as ſinfull as in the other: the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man hath abuſed one of Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Glutton many: Many a foggy Belly-god cryeth out of the ſwiniſh drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard (and deſeruedly) where he amongſt his diſhes is more ſwiniſh and beaſtly: <hi>The Beaſt exceedeth more in eating, then in drinking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22</hi> In the féeding of thy body, remember thy Soule: if thy body muſt needs periſh and pine for want of foode, ſo muſt thy Soule: the one is fed with corporall meat, the other with ſpirituall: <hi>The one is often
<pb facs="tcp:15030:8"/> fed, elſe it decaieth; ſo muſt the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">
               <hi>23</hi> Vſe recreation, yet ſuch as is honeſt and without offence: as thou wouldeſt not féede on ſuch meates as ſhould poiſon thy ſelfe, and thy enuenomed breath ſhould infect others: ſo vſe no ſuch recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as ſhall either infect thy owne ſelfe, or giue occaſion of corruption to others: <hi>Remember all lawfull things are not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24</hi> Vſe recreation when thou féeleſt a want of refreſhing of the Body or the Minde, not whenſoeuer thou deſireſt: for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted appetite is vnbridled, and muſt be reſtrained with Chriſtian diſcretion. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gallants, hauing wherewithall to maintaine themſelues, ſpend all their time in paſtimes: who, no leſſe offend, then if they did nothing but eate, drinke, or ſléepe: <hi>They ſit downe to eate, and drinke, and riſe vp</hi> (not to labour) <hi>but to play.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25</hi> If thou finde the flames of the fire of concupiſcence within thée, deferre not to
<pb facs="tcp:15030:8"/> marry: know that thou art called to that eſtate; and that as thou art bound by the Lawes of God, to abſtaine from fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, adulterie, and ſuch like vncleanneſſe; ſo thou art not only permitted, but bound to marry, when thou burneſt: <hi>Mariage is the ordinary meanes that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the remedy of Luſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26</hi> Say not thou art poore, and therefore if thou Marry, thou ſhalt impaire thy mirth, and vnder-goe many encumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: better the troubles of this life, then the fouleneſſe of the Minde: God will prouide for thée, if thou caſt thy care on him: Meaſure not the time of Mariage by the increaſe, or decreaſe of this wealth, but by the power thou haſt to containe, or haſt not to containe. <hi>A foole he is that ſaith when hee is rich, and not when hee is ſick, hee will prouide for a dangerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27</hi> Vſe thy Wife as a companion, not as a ſeruant; as ſhe is not the head, ſo ſhe is not the foote; ſhée was taken out néere to the heart, no out of the héele: As <hi>Shee is to
<pb facs="tcp:15030:9"/> be a comforter, not a controler:</hi> So <hi>Shee is to be a comfort, not a ſlaue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">
               <hi>28</hi> Yet ſuffer her not to be thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for thou art the head: yet diſdaine her not to be thy aduiſer in that which is good: and let her not rule neither by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe or command, in that which is euill. Haue diſcretion to diſtinguiſh betwéene wiſe <hi>Abigaile</hi> and vainglorious <hi>Eue,</hi> or <hi>Iobes</hi> fooliſh wife: <hi>A good Woman makes a good Man better,</hi> and <hi>An euill Woman an ill man worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">
               <hi>29</hi> Although ſhée haue many faults (whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome excepted) yet forſake her not: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be carefull before-hand to chuſe for vertue, not for beauty: thou haſt taken her for better and for worſe: <hi>A wiſe Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman if he haue a barren Field and full of thorns, ſtraight putteth it not away, but laboureth with all skill, care, and diligent culture to amend it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">
               <hi>30</hi> Féed not, nor cloathe more finely or daintily then ſhée: but as ſhée is thy yoke-fellow, to helpe beare the labours and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<pb facs="tcp:15030:9"/> of this life, ſo <hi>Let her be partaker with thee in the fruits of your labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">
               <hi>31</hi> Be abſtinent in ſleeping, for conſcience ſake, as in eating or drinking; for God is offended by the exceſſe of the one as well as of the other: as thou oughteſt not to eate or drinke ſo long as the belly will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue or hold, ſo oughteſt thou not to ſléepe ſo long as thou canſt or deſireſt: he which ſléepeth ouer-much, is not only lazie, but ſinfull; and he which ſléepeth leaſt, ſlée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth néere halfe his time. <hi>Halfe the time of thy life thou reſteſt in the ſhadow of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">
               <hi>32</hi> Neuer account him thy friend, that ſpeakes thée alwayes faire, for theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Firſt, moſt commonly, the faireſt ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are but flatteries, procéeding from a filthy and diſſembling heart: Secondly, he cannot be a friend which alwaies ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faire; for a friend muſt be like a good Phyſitian, who ſometimes purgeth and ſometimes reſtoreth: ſo <hi>A true friend; ſometimes comforteth, and ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">
               <hi>33</hi> Bear with thy friend in many things, and account him not thy friend that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not with thée likewiſe: loue couereth
<pb facs="tcp:15030:10"/> a multitude of offences: <hi>True brotherly Charity conſiſteth not only in doing, but alſo in ſuffering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">
               <hi>34</hi> Séek and enquire earneſtly for a true friend, for he is a iewell not eaſily to be found; and when thou findeſt, try before thou truſt, for no iewell adorning the life of man is more ſophiſticated then friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and when thou tryeſt him, try him in aduerſity: for as moſt men are louers of proſperity, ſo many will loue thée to be partakers of thy happineſſe. <hi>Friendſhip is tryed as faith; in hoping, not in hauing; in woe, not in wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">
               <hi>35</hi> Haue not many frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, for tis a thing impoſſible to haue many and true; but if thou haue, thou art the happieſt man on earth, and ſhall be chronicled for a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: <hi>Many haue liued hauing not one, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any that yet had many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">
               <hi>36</hi> Prouoke no man to be thine aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but ſo much as in thée lies, haue peace with all men: In prouoking an enemie thou procureſt thine owne harme, and ſuffereſt rather as an euill doer, then as an innocent, and ſo loſeſt the recompence of thine afflictions: if thou prouokeſt an enemie, thou ſtirreſt vp his rage, and by
<pb facs="tcp:15030:10"/> conſequence, art a meanes to prouoke his wicked and iniurious dealing and ſo alſo by neceſſary conſequence his iudgement, which is contrary to Charitie: <hi>Charitie commandeth to be a meanes to help, not to hurt the body, much more the Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">
               <hi>37</hi> Beware of the violence &amp; ſubtilty of thine aduerſary, that it hurt thée not: but if thou muſt needs be wronged of him, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yeeld that his force hurt thy body, then that his allurements or thy impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hurt thy Soule: the dammages of the Soule are more irreparable then the harmes of the body; that his oppreſſions endammage thy goods, then that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports diſparage thy fame: <hi>For a good Name is to be choſen aboue great Riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="38">
               <hi>38</hi> When thou beholdeſt Gods iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts fall on thine aduerſary, giue God thanks for thy deliuerance; but yet reioyce not at his affliction: for this diſpleaſeth God, to whom vengeance belongeth; and it is a iuſt iudgement of God to thruſt him into the ſtead, that is glad of his enemies fall. <hi>Charity rather deſireth deliuerance with the ſafetie of the perſecutor, then with his deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="39">
               <hi>39</hi> Fret not at the riches, honor, or proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="tcp:15030:11"/> of thine enemie; alas, they are but ſnares, they may be his portion, which he hath only in this life: thy portion is farre greater, peace of Conſcience in this world, &amp; euerlaſting bliſſe in the world to come. <hi>A folly that the leane Cow ſhould fret at the fat: Shee being leane, is reſerued for encreaſe; the other being fat, is appointed to the ſlaughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="40">
               <hi>40</hi> Obey thy parents, yea, although they be wicked. As is the King vnto his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ſo is the Father to his Children, ſet ouer them by God, and Gods ordinance: as therefore wée muſt obey euen euill Princes for conſcience ſake, as the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God ſo alſo muſt wée bée obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent euen to wicked Parents, as ſet ouer vs of God, <hi>And he that diſobeyeth them, cannot be excuſable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">
               <hi>41</hi> Yet obey not thy pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in that which is contrary to the Word of God: who commandeth things vnlawfull, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not as a Father, but as an enemy; not as the ſubſtitute of God, but as the inſtrument of Sathan: in this caſe, thou muſt <hi>Forſake Father and Mother and all, for Chriſts ſake; and profeſſe that thou haſt but one Father which is in Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="42">
               <pb facs="tcp:15030:11"/>
               <hi>42</hi> Yéeld vnto thy Parents not only ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and obedience, but reliefe alſo in their neceſſities: thou haſt receiued from them, next vnder God, thy body, thy bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thy maintenance, and canſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite their kindneſſe whatſoeuer thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſince <hi>Thou canſt not beget, beare, and bring forth them as they haue thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="43">
               <hi>43</hi> Contemn not thy ſtep-father or ſtep-mother, thou oweſt them duty, as thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall parents: <hi>As I will make it plaine by inſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, thy mother hauing marryed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, he and ſhe by mariage are made one fleſh, thou oweſt therefore to one and the ſelfe ſame fleſh, one and the ſelfe ſame duty; <hi>And ſo if thy Father marry another woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thou hauing married a wife, art by mariage with her, one fleſh, and therefore one fleſh hath alſo one father and one mother; how can one fleſh although in two perſons, not honor one and the ſelfe ſame parents: <hi>So is it to a woman that hath married an husband.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="44">
               <hi>44</hi> Regard thy maſter as the inſtrument of God to teach thée that knowledge, which God himſelfe without the miniſtry
<pb facs="tcp:15030:12"/> of any maſter did teach thy forefathers, <hi>Arts and Sciences are the gifts of God, and Maſters are the miniſters of God, as from him to impart them to vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="45">
               <hi>45</hi> Loue, obey, and honour thy Maſter &amp; thy Miſtreſſe acknowledge Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in them, that he hath ſet them ouer thée: thy parents hauing giuen thee, vnder God thy being, <hi>They alſo, vnder him giue thee thy being skilfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="46">
               <hi>46</hi> Behaue thy ſelf to thy fellow ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as to thy yoake-fellowes, willing to helpe them beare the burden as thou wouldeſt be holpen; if any be more skilfull then thy ſelfe, and thy elder, reſpect the gifts of God in him: if leſſe skilfull, and thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, regard him as in the hopefull way to knowledge: crow not ouer, nor oppreſſe ſuch a one, but remember that when thou thy ſelfe hadſt thy beginnings, thou wouldeſt haue beene loth to haue beene op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p n="47">
               <hi>47</hi> Accompany not with a lewd fellow-ſeruant, otherwiſe then in your neceſſary labours, leſt thou loſe thine owne recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, &amp; receiue of his ſtripes: <hi>The gentle Oxe draweth with the vnruly, but rangeth not with him when he is out of the yoke,
<pb facs="tcp:15030:12"/> leſt alſo with him he be turned off to the ſlaughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="48">
               <hi>48</hi> Learne rightly to diſtinguiſh betwixt Faith and Preſumption: for <hi>as there is no meanes without the one vnto ſaluation, ſo there is but one meanes beſide the other to damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="49">
               <hi>49</hi> As before the fact to ſay, <hi>The Lord doubtleſſe wil be mercifull to me in this,</hi> is preſumption: ſo to ſay after the fact, <hi>The Lord doubtleſſe will ſhew mercy,</hi> if ioyned with repentance, is faith, if without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is alſo preſumption.</p>
            <p n="50">
               <hi>50</hi> Make vſe of Gods mercy with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, not with malepartneſſe, <hi>Though God be mercifull, yet he is mighty &amp; iuſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="51">
               <hi>51</hi> Continue not in ſinne, for <hi>God is iuſt:</hi> yet deſpaire not though thou haſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſinned, for <hi>God is alſo mercifull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="52">
               <hi>52</hi> When thou haſt grieuouſly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, be not leſſe confident to obtaine Gods mercy, then when thou hadſt leſſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: for <hi>By how much the more thou haſt ſinned, by ſo much the more thou art in thy ſelfe miſerable: and by how much the more miſerable thou art, by ſo much the more pittifull is God: and by how much the more pittifull, by ſo much the more
<pb facs="tcp:15030:13"/> mercifull is hee</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="53">
               <hi>53</hi> Make not light of ſinne becauſe God is mercifull: a Kings pardon is not to be played withall, but with reuerence to be receiued. <hi>Gods grace by how much the more abundant, by ſo much the more to be reſpected, and not abuſed</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="54">
               <hi>54</hi> Procure the loue of all men ſo far as with a good conſcience thou maiſt: but if thou muſt néeds incur hatred, be hated of the euill rather then of the good: for <hi>The hatred of the euill is a probable ſigne of Gods loue, the hatred of the good of Gods diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="55">
               <hi>55</hi> The hatred of the good may many wayes endammage thee, the hatred of the euill cannot hurt thée, though for a time it may afflict thee: for, <hi>God for whoſe ſake thou art hated, ſhall turne their curſe into a bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="56">
               <hi>56</hi> Loue whom thou loueſt vnfainedly: the good for Gods ſake, and as the children of God, to whom let thy loue be without diſſimulation, as it is to their father: the euill either by kindneſſe or reprehenſions to amend them: ſo ſhalt thou <hi>ſhew thy ſelfe a builder in Gods worke, and not a plucker downe; a planter in Gods Garden, not a ſupplanter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="57">
               <pb facs="tcp:15030:13"/>
               <hi>57</hi> If thou féeleſt the ſwéetneſſe of Gods mercies abundantly, be not careleſſe and héedleſſe of his iudgements; God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned by the careleſſe reſpect of any of his attributes. As his mercies are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, if by Faith his loue in Ieſus Chriſt be not apprehended: ſo his power is deſpiſed, when his iudgements bee not feared <hi>Gods iudgements await thoſe nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which by any meanes goe aſtray in the abundance of his fauours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="58">
               <hi>58</hi> If thou haſt offended God, be carefull to amend in the time to come, then ſhall thy former iniquities be blotted out of his Regiſter, and thy preſent righteouſneſſe be regarded of him in Chriſt: for God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth not what a man hath beene, but what he is, <hi>As the Tree falleth ſo it lyeth; as God finds a man, ſo he takes him. Hee that hath a heauy burthen on his ſhoulders already, if he deſire to be eaſed, muſt lay vp no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="59">
               <hi>59</hi> Think it not ſufficient to amend thy life in the time to come, but alſo reconcile thy ſelfe to God by faith, an' true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for that which is paſt: the New man is not put on, before the Old man is put off: <hi>He that will be eaſed of a heauy burden,
<pb facs="tcp:15030:14"/> muſt not only heape vp no more, but caſt off that which is vpon him already.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="60">
               <hi>60</hi> Defer not thy repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to thy death-bed or laſt houre, that is the time of thy paſſage to giue vp thy accounts, not the time of deliberation to make it vp; at that time the body is not onely weakned, but the mind: and not only weakned, but alſo diſturbed: <hi>Woe to thoſe wretches which in the houre of death, firſt deſire to learne an Art ſo hard and intricate, <hi>viz.</hi> The Art of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling and vniting themſelues to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="61">
               <hi>61</hi> If thou féele in thy ſelfe a diſtruſt of Gods loue, &amp; an vnſtedfaſt perſwaſion of thy ſaluation; examine and trie thy ſelfe whether it be not by reaſon of ſundry ſins which thou foſtereſt in thy boſome, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of nor forſaken: for then as thy conſcience preacheth peace for thy refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in ſome things, it wil preach iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for thy want of reformation in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and becauſe thy greateſt vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cannot ſaue thée, but thy leaſt ſin is able to condemne thée; thou ſhalt not féele the comforts of ſauing health from thine imperfect reformation, but ſhalt ſée the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of Gods iudgements awai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy defects. <hi>That which cannot ſaue,
<pb facs="tcp:15030:14"/> will not preach peace, but that which can condemne, will preach iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="62">
               <hi>62</hi> In thy practice of repentance, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and forſake all thy ſins, if thou wilt be at perfect peace with God, thou muſt make a final end of al controuerſies: <hi>Thou muſt bury altogether all matters of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not begin them againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="63">
               <hi>63</hi> Be not partaker with the vngodly in his ſinnes yet pry not more into others faults then into thine owne: the curious ſearching into other mens eſtates which appertaines not to thée, is a principall meanes to cauſe thee neglect the due exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and tryall of thy ſelfe. <hi>If euery man would looke carefully into his owne garden, he ſhould finde ſo many weeds to be plucked vp therein, that hee ſhould not need curiouſly to wander into another mans field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="64">
               <hi>64</hi> Iudge no man raſhly to be damned, or a Reprobate; for although there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fearfull preſumptions in a prophane life of reprobation; yet but one infallible token, which is the ſinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for all other ſins whatſoeuer may be forgiuen: <hi>Thou mayeſt ſee how the tree ſtandeth in preſent; but knoweſt not how
<pb facs="tcp:15030:15"/> through Gods mercy he may fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="65">
               <hi>65</hi> Flatter not thy ſelfe that it is but a foolery to be in thy life preciſe &amp; careful: for as there is a difference betwéene heauen &amp; hel, ſo there muſt be between y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profeſſors of either. <hi>The childrens bread is not for dogs, nor the ioyes of heauen for the prophane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="66">
               <hi>66</hi> Be carefull rather to be preciſe in life then in profeſſion; yet ſo preciſe in profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion alſo, as not to bluſh at the words and workes of piety. <hi>Preciſeneſſe in profeſſion without the life, is a Chriſtians tongue without a Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="67">
               <hi>67</hi> Let the inward féeling of Gods mercies towards thée in Chriſt, be an aſſurance of his fatherly prouiſion for thée in things of this life: for although Gods eſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and outward proſperitie doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hold hands; yet muſt his fatherly care in the greater be aſſurance of his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer failing care in the leſſer: <hi>He which is ready to giue vnto thee heauenly things, ſhall hee not giue thee earthly; doeſt thou rely on him for the one, and wilt thou not truſt him for the other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="68">
               <hi>68</hi> In matters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning thy ſouls health, be aduiſed by him that is a man of God. But thou wilt aſke how thou ſhalt know
<pb facs="tcp:15030:15"/> him? I anſwer, if he be humble and méeke like his Maſter: but how ſhalt thou know whether he be humble &amp; méeke? I anſwer, if he be proud &amp; ſtately in his cariage, he is not humble and méeke in his heart: <hi>For although there be counterfeited humility, yet there is no counterfeited pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="69">
               <hi>69</hi> If thou obtain not preſently what thou deſireſt at the hand of God, bée not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged: God in with-holding his hand, doth not onely try thy patience, but alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his gifts: <hi>Thoſe things are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the meaneſt which are ſooneſt obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but thoſe the moſt precious which are moſt hardly procured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="70">
               <hi>70</hi> Loue God zealouſly, yet without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall expectation of reward: for although thy loue towards God ſhall not bee vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced, yet ought it not to worke for recompence: <hi>For loue ſeeketh not his own, it is no mercinary contract.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="71">
               <hi>71</hi> Account it the moſt fearfull eſtate of life to liue without croſſes and afflictions; for when parents doe not ſcourge their children, either they let them alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebuke to run headlong into all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and from thence to deſtruction; or elſe they haue renounced them as baſtards
<pb facs="tcp:15030:16"/> and none of thoſe that ſhall any longer bee partakers of their fatherly care or loue thus to be dealt withall by an earthly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is dangerous and grieuous: <hi>But much more ſo to be left to our ſelues of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="72">
               <hi>72</hi> Flatter not thy ſelfe in thy ſins, that it ſhall not be for Gods glory to confound thée being ſo ſéely a creature: for God is glorified by the deſtruction of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as alſo hée is by the ſaluation of the righteous: the righteous in his ſaluation is exalted with God, when God and his elect are exalted in the fall of the wicked, remember this vndoubted truth, <hi>Thy wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe hurteth not God but thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="73">
               <hi>73</hi> Auoid the company and inward famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity with the vngodly, as thou wouldeſt auoid the ſtrokes of Gods iudgements: <hi>For when two embrace each other arme in arme, it is hard that the ſtroke that hitteth the one ſhould miſſe the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="74">
               <hi>74</hi> Lament not with exceſſiue ſorrow the death of any friend, if thou feare their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of Gods fauour; as thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers cannot redeeme them, ſo thy ſorrow cannot help thy ſelfe or them. If they be departed in the fauour of God, let thy ioy
<pb facs="tcp:15030:16"/> for their happineſſe requite thy loſſe. If thou be doubtfull of their eſtate, thou haſt not cauſe to reioyce at that which perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture is not, nor to ſorrow at that which perhaps hath not hapned, <hi>But in Charitie to hope the beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="75">
               <hi>75</hi> Learne to diſtinguiſh truly betwéen ſecuritie and true peace of conſcience: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie feeleth no danger, &amp; hath no feare; Peace of conſcience féeleth and feares, but ouercommeth and reioyceth in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Gods fauour: <hi>That thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be moſt void of care, take heed of Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: no man feeleth his owne force in the time of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="76">
               <hi>76</hi> Feare not death although he be griſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the grim ſir though he bring ill newes paſt, yet he brings good newes to come: many an ill man feares not the Deuill when he leads him to an earthly treaſure, <hi>And ſhall a good man feare Death when he opens him the doore to heauenly ioyes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="77">
               <hi>77</hi> Poſſeſſe not thy mind with the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh feare of the dead, or the company of a carkaſe: a good man will not hurt thée dead or liuing: <hi>An ill man may well hurt thee when hee is aliue, but cannot harme thee when he is dead and not able to helpe himſelfe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="78">
               <pb facs="tcp:15030:17"/>
               <hi>78</hi> Deſire rather to liue poorely and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, then richly and diſhoneſtly: poore honeſty gets a richer purchaſe then rich diſhoneſty; the one purchaſeth heauen, which is the gaines of all; the other hell, which is the loſſe of all: honeſt ſorrow pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth greater comfort then diſhoneſt ioy: <hi>For more comfort ſhall a man reape at his latter end by one houre ſpent in Gods ſeruice, then by many yeares ſpent in vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="79">
               <hi>79</hi> Suffer not thine eyes to wander too large, nor thy tongue to walke too faſt: for as the beſt meanes to preſerue the body in health, is to kéepe the eyes open and the mouth ſhut; ſo the beſt meanes for the good of the ſoule, is to <hi>ſhut the caſements of the one, and to ſet a watch before the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="80">
               <hi>80</hi> Auoid the company of a contentious man, hée is a perilous euill in two reſpects; for either he will contend with thée, and ſo thou ſhalt procure the ſtroke of the edge of his malice, or elſe prouoke thée to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with others, and ſo thou ſhalt for his loue get the hatred of many. <hi>A peny is deare bought with a pound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="81">
               <hi>81</hi> In ſéeking to perſwade thy friend to forſake any wicked courſe, begin firſt
<pb facs="tcp:15030:17"/> with kindneſſe, it may preuaile without reprehenſions; hée is a fooliſh Phyſitian who if he can cure with mollifying Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſmes, will vſe painful Cauteries: repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions take the better place, where kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath led the way. <hi>The body which hath bin ſtrengthened with a cordiall doth the better beare out a violent purgation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="82">
               <hi>82</hi> Séeke for the lawfull aſſiſtance of Phyſick in the time of ſickneſſe, it is as néedfull and as lawfull, as to ſéeke for meate and drinke in the time of hunger and thirſt: <hi>God hath giuen to euery Plant his ſeuerall vertue, not for nothing, but for the health of the body, as of the ſelfe-ſame Spirit there are ſundry operations for the health of the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="83">
               <hi>83</hi> Deferre not the Chriſtening of any Childe, though thou be compelled to doe it in thy owne houſe: <hi>Whereſoeuer two or three bee gathered together in Chriſtes Name, hee is in the midſt amongſt them.</hi> The little Childe muſt not be denied to come to Chriſt; who cannot by the word, muſt by Baptiſme: though thou mightſt falſly obiect, the Baptiſme helpeth it not; <hi>Yet ſo it becomes vs to fulfill all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="84">
               <pb facs="tcp:15030:18"/>
               <hi>84</hi> Loue, honour, and obey thy Prince, dearely, reuerently, carefully: he is <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> the father of the Countrie, thou one of his children, if his ſubiect: <hi>Thy good and ſafetie is a part of that heauy burden of care that lyeth on his ſhoulders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="85">
               <hi>85</hi> Loue alſo, honour and obey the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; they are the eyes of God, for they are his watch-men; they are the mouth of God, for <hi>They are his ſpeech-men, meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and Embaſſadors for Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="86">
               <hi>86</hi> Loue alſo, honour and obey all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates vnder thy Prince, they are as the members of his Body, whereby hée worketh thy good and ſafety; thy Prince and the Magiſtrates his ſubſtitutes are the hand of God which carieth the ſword of Iuſtice to puniſh the offender. <hi>And the purſe of reward to recompence the good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="87">
               <hi>87</hi> Giue vnto the godly his due praiſe for his goodneſſe; who doth well, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth praiſe of all; and who deſerueth praiſe of all, deſerueth praiſe of thée: pay him therefore his due and right, otherwiſe <hi>thou doſt ſhew thy ſelfe iniurious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="88">
               <hi>88</hi> Commend not the vngodlineſſe of the wicked man: better it is in loue to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer many ſinnes, then in flattery to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb facs="tcp:15030:18"/> one: to commend that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, is to make God a lyar and vniuſt, which both diſcommendeth and puniſheth it: To commend that which is euill, is to iniury the good and innocent, <hi>viz. <hi>To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his portion on the vnworthy, and to rob him of his due, and to make thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker with him in his reward, that haue not laboured with him in his worke.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="89">
               <hi>89</hi> Be not haſty to reueale the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of thy brethren, eſpecially of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: for, whereas therein thou thinkeſt to doe iuſtly, thou mayſt notwithſtanding doe very wickedly in cauſing a ſcandall to ariſe at Religion which cannot ſo ſoone be healed, as the offence of thy brother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concealed by ſecret admonition might haue béen ſalued; thereby, not onely the offence of thy Miniſter ſhall be lothed, but alſo himſelfe and his doctrine ſo much ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, as <hi>that many a ſauing admonition of his ſhall be ſuſpected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="90">
               <hi>90</hi> Eſtéeme not thy ſelfe out of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of God, becauſe thou art hated, diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſlandered, perſecuted, poore and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; for thy Maſter Chriſt was poore, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, diſliked, perſecuted, ſlandered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; yet he moſt highly in Gods fauor,
<pb facs="tcp:15030:19"/> and thou for his ſake: <hi>When therefore for his ſake thou art hated, diſliked, ſlandered, poore, perſecuted and deſpiſed, thou art ſure to be higheſt in his fauour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="91">
               <hi>91</hi> Yet boaſt not of thy ſufferings: when thou ſuffereſt for thy deſerts, thou recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt not enough for thy ſinne, thy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is iuſt: thy cauſe requireth mercy, thy ſufferings challenge not recompence: <hi>It is the cauſe and not the puniſhment that makes a Martyr, the Theefe was hanged for his murder, as well as Chriſt for the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="92">
               <hi>92</hi> Yet diſtruſt not of Gods mercy when thou ſuffereſt for thy deſerts: Gods elect haue béene puniſhed for their ſinnes and follies, yet haue comforted themſelues with the hope of Gods fauor. <hi>It is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of fatherly care and loue when the childe is chaſtened for his faults; all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments whatſoeuer, are to the penitent but chaſtiſements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="93">
               <hi>93</hi> Thinke not vaingloriouſly to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy reputation, without the feare of God; an vngodly life maketh the greateſt gifts thou haſt become contemptible: Wiſdome doth more dignitie a poore man then riches a foole. <hi>No man dareth to touch
<pb facs="tcp:15030:19"/> the hayres of a King, whilſt they are on his head, in ſcorne: but being once cut off, they are caſt with others vnto the dunghill, and trodden vnder foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="94">
               <hi>94</hi> Obiect not againſt this aduiſe: but thoſe that fear not God, are in theſe times in greateſt eſtéeme: for of whom are they eſtéemed? of themſelues; and therefore of no indifferent Iudges; of thoſe that are like themſelues, and therefore of no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Iudges: <hi>Not of God nor of the good, and therefore not rightly eſteemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="95">
               <hi>95</hi> Harken not to fame what others ſay of thee, ſo much as to thine owne hart what it doth witneſſe of thee: fame may flatter thee cauſleſſe or condemn thee vniuſtly, but <hi>Thine owne heart ſhall tell the whole truth without flattery and falſhood, which none but God and thy ſelfe is priuy to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="96">
               <hi>96</hi> Thinke it not ſufficient to ſorrow for thy ſins, and to hate and deteſt them; but know that thou muſt ſtriue againſt them, and ouercome thy corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>A mortal enemy is not ſubdued when hee is hated, but when hee is reſiſted; nor when hee is reſiſted, vnleſſe hee be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="97">
               <hi>97</hi> Féed not on delights haſtily, nor
<pb facs="tcp:15030:20"/> when thou taſteſt them with gréedineſſe: there is no poyſon like to the ſwéeteſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is moſt gréedily deuoured, <hi>And moſt ſpeedily conueyed into all parts of the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="98">
               <hi>98</hi> Be as ſparing in perſecuting, yea the euill (if thou be no Magiſtrate) with the ſafety of Gods glory, and thine owne life and eſtate as thou canſt: Let the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate call thée to the bar, call not thou him; ouermuch raſhneſſe and haſtineſſe in perſecuting is a ſhrewd preſumption of a malignant ſpirit, as a learned Father hath notably obſerued, that <hi>Cain</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Abel;</hi> not <hi>Abel, Cain: Abſolom, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid;</hi> not <hi>Dauid, Abſolom:</hi> the <hi>Iewes, Chriſt;</hi> not <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Iewes. A mild ſpirit rather ſuffereth then doth violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="99">
               <hi>99</hi> Account it a greater happineſſe to ſuffer wrong then to doe iniurie; if thou ſuffer wrong, thou art of the number of thoſe whom Chriſt hath pronounced bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: <hi>If thou doe wrong, of thoſe which he hath denounced curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="100">
               <hi>100</hi> Let this ſhort prayer be often ſent the Embaſſador of the deſire of thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull ſoule, to the throne of Grace: <hi>Lord I am a moſt grieuous ſinner, therefore moſt
<pb facs="tcp:15030:20"/> miſerable: but by how much the more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, by ſo much be thou the more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to put away my ſinnes, and to cure my miſeries, and to renew me and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me with thy grace, in the courſe of my life hereafter, that I may not onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauor, but delight to glorifie thee, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore I haue beene accuſtomed and haue delighted to diſhonour thee. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <l>IN thy Religion be ſincere,</l>
            <l>and ſeeme but what thou art:</l>
            <l>For God that made thee fully knowes,</l>
            <l>thy inward thoughts and heart.</l>
            <l>Yeeld to thy parents honor due,</l>
            <l>their needs ſee thou relieue,</l>
            <l>And wiſely rule thy ſelfe alway,</l>
            <l>leſt thou their age doſt grieue.</l>
            <l>Thy wife as a companion fit,</l>
            <l>not like a ſeruant vſe:</l>
            <l>Yet let her not rule ouer thee,</l>
            <l>leſt thou thy place abuſe.</l>
            <l>A friend doe neuer him eſteeme</l>
            <l>that alwayes ſpeakes thee faire,</l>
            <l>For he a friend is for himſelfe,</l>
            <l>and nought for thee doth care.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:21"/>
            <l>But make thou much account of him</l>
            <l>that plainly will reproue,</l>
            <l>When ought amiſſe in thee he ſees,</l>
            <l>for that is ſigne of loue.</l>
            <l>For many a one in vice run on,</l>
            <l>and thinke they nought offend,</l>
            <l>Becauſe that claw backes flatter them,</l>
            <l>and none will reprehend.</l>
            <l>Be thy vocation high or low,</l>
            <l>or whatſoere thou art,</l>
            <l>With conſcience mannage thy affaires,</l>
            <l>and vprightneſſe of heart.</l>
            <l>Defraud no man by any meanes,</l>
            <l>take heed none thee deceiue,</l>
            <l>The Doue and Serpent thinke vpon</l>
            <l>if thou wilt rightly liue.</l>
            <l>Of th'Iudgement day and laſt account,</l>
            <l>ſee thou ſtill mindfull be.</l>
            <l>That ſin thou maiſt the better ſhun,</l>
            <l>and all lewd courſes flee:</l>
            <l>So ſhalt thou lead a happy life</l>
            <l>while God a place doth lend,</l>
            <l>And afterwards receiue a Crowne</l>
            <l>which neuer ſhall haue end.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15030:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
